Guide to the Montana Military Veterans Oral History Project 1993-2002
Montana Historical Society Research Center
- ELDORA MCBRIDE INTERVIEW, OH 1279; 1 tape(s), Transcript 26 pages
  Eldora McBride (b. 1923) discusses her childhood; attending Northern Montana College, Havre, Montana; medical secretary training; enlisting in the U.S. Navy in 1944; military training in Hunter College, New York; racial discrimination; women and promotions in the military; uniforms; living conditions; transfer to Medical Center in Bethesda, Maryland and later to naval facility at Corvallis, Oregon; war; transferring to Naval Air Base in Seattle, Washington; GI bill educational benefits; and life after military service. Interviewed by Rosetta Kamlowsky, May 28, 1992, Helena, MT.
- HERBERT GOODWIN INTERVIEW, OH 1280; 2 tape(s), Transcript 40 pages
  Herbert Goodwin (b. 1919) discusses his early life in Canada; service with the Canadian Army; experiences with combined Canadian and American First Special Service Forces during World War II; training at Fort William Henry Harrison; the Kiska Island Landing; various European operations; and his recollections of General Robert T. Frederick. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 17, 1992, Helena, MT.
- MABEL HAYNES INTERVIEW, OH 1376; 1 tape(s), Transcript 5 pages
  Mabel Haynes discusses her family and early life in Judith Gap, Montana; father's ownership and operation of First National Bank with C.R. Stone; the Hayes Store; Stone/ Gaugler Ranch; education; enlistment and service with U.S. Marine Corps as an aircraft control tower operator during World War II; and women in the military. Interviewed by Jennifer Peterson, December 1, 1991, Judith Gap, MT.
- WILLIAM NIELSEN INTERVIEW, OH 1378; 1 tape(s), Summary 5 pages
  William Nielsen (b. 1939) discusses his family and early life in Lewistown, Montana; enlisting in the United States Navy; service aboard surface ships and submarines; the Vietnam War; the rescue of downed U.S. pilots and aircrew; later military service and retirement; and views on the Vietnam War and Operation Desert Storm. Interviewed by Shannon Plovanic, December 1, 1991, Stanford, MT.
- JEANNE LECLAIR ROBINETTE INTERVIEW, OH 1381; 1 tape(s), Transcript 10 pages
  Jeanne LeClair Robinette (b. 1920) discusses her family and early life in Delphia, Montana; education; work at Boeing Aircraft's Seattle, Washington plant during World War II; return to Montana after the war; her nursing career; and retirement. Interviewed by Monica Brewington, December 6, 1991, Ballantine, MT.
- GERALD MCFADDEN INTERVIEW, OH 1391; 1 tape(s), Transcript 10 pages
  Gerald McFadden discusses his experiences as a soldier in the Canadian Army and First Special Service Forces during World War II; special training at Fort Harrison, Montana; and his recollections of the Anzio campaign. Interviewed by John Terreo, August 19, 1992, Helena, MT.
- JOHN C. HARRISON INTERVIEW, OH 1453; 2 tape(s), Transcript 46 pages
  John C. Harrison (b. 1913) discusses his service with the U.S. Army prior to and during World War II; experiences as a staff officer with VII Corps; D-Day preparations; investigations of atrocities against U.S. military personnel by German military and civilians, including the Malemedy Massacre; meetings with Montanans John Bonner and Lee Metcalf; liberation of concentration camps at Nordhausen and Torgau; and preparations for the invasion of Japan. Interviewed by John Terreo, January 29, 1992, Helena, MT.
- SUSAN GIBB INTERVIEW, OH 1455; 1 tape(s), Transcript 2 pages
  Susan Gibb (b. 1946) of Hysham, Montana recalls personal theories and philosophies of military leadership, and recollections of returning home to Hysham following her retirement. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 20, 1993, Helena, MT.
- DAVID SAYRE INTERVIEW, OH 1457; 2 tape(s), Transcript 46 pages
  David Sayre (b. 1948) discusses his experiences as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment during Operation Desert Storm/Shield; the division of the unit into two cells; the 3rd Armored Calvary Regiment; duties as First Sergeant; living and working conditions; and other military issues. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 1, 1991, Fort Harrison, MT.
- DAVID SAYRE INTERVIEW, OH 1458; 2 tape(s), Transcript 36 pages
  David Sayre (b. 1948) discusses growing up in Glasgow, Montana; joining the U.S. Marine Corps; experiences with the special Montana Training Platoon; marine boot camp; infantry training; experiences during Vietnam with 26th Marine Regiment; the Seige of Khe Sanh; and U.S. military involvement in Southeast Asia. Interviewed by John Terreo, March 3, 1992, Great Falls, MT.
- PATRICK MOHAN INTERVIEW, OH 1459; 2 tape(s), Transcript 48 pages
  Patrick Mohan (b. 1948) discusess his experiences as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment during Operation Desert Shield/Storm; division of unit into two cells; experiences with 3rd Armored Calvary Regiment; responsibilities as one a cell officer; living and working conditions; the return home. Interviewed by John Terreo, August 1991,
- KAREENE OSTERMILLER INTERVIEW, OH 1463; 5 tape(s), Transcript 120 pages
  Kareene Ostermiller discusses her experiences as the only woman member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment in Operation Desert Shield/Storm; women in military service; women in American and Arab cultures; women as leaders; gender issues; racial and sexual harrassment; desert life; daily activities; and her homecoming. Interviewed by John Terreo, August 4, 1992, Shepard, MT
- TERRANCE YOUNG INTERVIEW, OH 1464; 2 tape(s), Transcript 44 pages
  Terrance Young discusses his experiences as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment attached to 18th Airborne Corps Artillery; his refresher training at Fort Lewis, Washington; arriving in Saudi Arabia; the "Cement City"; living conditions and unit operations; technology; and his homecoming. Interviewed by John Terreo, November 18, 1992, Helena, MT.
- CHARLES "MILO" MCLEOD INTERVIEW, OH 1465; 2 tape(s), Transcript 38 pages
  Charles McLeod (b. 1947) discusses his experiences as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment in Operation Desert Shield/Storm; the division of the unit into two cells; the 3rd Armored Calvary Regiment; living and working conditions in desert environment; Meals Ready to Eat (MRE); working with civilian media; and readjusting to civilian life. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 1, 1991, Helena, MT.
- TODD BUHMILLER INTERVIEW, OH 1466; 4 tape(s)
  This is a follow-up interview conducted with Todd Buhmiller (b. 1963) after the return of his unit from Operation Desert Storm. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 11, 1992, Helena, MT.
- GREG FOX INTERVIEW, OH 1468; 1 tape(s), Transcript 34 pages
  Greg Fox (b. 1953) discusses his work in Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm with the Montana National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment; his assignment to the 3rd Armored Calvary Regiment; refresher training at Fort Lewis Washington; arrival at "Cement City"; the division of his unit into two cells; attitudes of regular army toward military and civilian media; unit activites and operations; escort of civilian media; desert living conditions; return home; opinions about conflict. Interviewed by John Terreo, February 1992
- PATRICK HERMANSON INTERVIEW, OH 1469; 2 tape(s), Transcript 45 pages
  Patrick Hermanson, a Billings, Montana Resident, discusses his experiences as during Operation Desert Shield/Storm as Commanding Officer of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment. Interviewed by John Terreo, August 3, 1993, Billings, MT
- JODIE YELTON INTERVIEW, OH 1470; 3 tape(s), Transcript 82 pages
  Jodie Yelton (b. 1948) discusses his experiences as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment in Operation Desert Shield/Storm; the division of his unit into two cells; living and working conditions; his assignment as his cell's First Sergeant; duties and responsibilities of that position; his experiences with XVIII Airborne Corps Artillery; readjusting to civilian life; and his personal opinion of conflict. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 1991
- ANDY LEE JOHNSON INTERVIEW, OH 1471; 1 tape(s), Transcript 32 pages
  Andy Johnson (b. 1948) discusses his experiences as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment during Operation Desert Shield/Storm; his unit's arrival at "Cement City"; serving as media escort for Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS) television correspondent Bob Martin; living and working conditions in the desert; Meals Ready to Eat (MREs); and the role of the military media. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 1, 1991, Fort Harrison, MT.
- MARY FELDER INTERVIEW, OH 1472; 1 tape(s), Transcript 4 pages
  Mary Felder (b. 1918) briefly describes her service in the United States Navy Hospital Corps, and her life at the Montana Veterans Home in Columbia Falls, Montana. Interviewed by Kari Nelson, May, 23, 1990, Columbia Falls, MT.
- JUANITA COOKE INTERVIEW, OH 1473; 1 tape(s), Transcript 19 pages
  Juanita Cooke (1910-1998) discusses her early flying lessons; landing a malfunctioning P-40 fighter plane in Billings airport; the rules and regulations for military ferry flights; experiences as a WASP Squadron Commander; difficulties flying a B-25 medium bomber and instrument flying a C-47 transport plane; aircraft instrument panels; WASP uniforms; the deactivation of the WASPs in December 1944; and life following World War II. Interviewed by John Terreo, May 8, 1991, Helena, MT.
- FRANK BACKBONE INTERVIEW, OH 1521; 2 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  Frank Backbone (b. 1917), a member of the Crow Indian Tribe, discusses his service with the U.S. Army during World War II; his posting to 91st Infantry Division; fighting near Rome, in Po Valley, and Boulange; getting wounded; and life after his honorable discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College.] Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 1, 1991, Crow Agency, MT
- CHARLES BROWN, JR. INTERVIEW, OH 1522; 1 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  Charles Brown, Jr. (b. 1921) discusses his service with the U.S. Army 127th Infantry Division during World War II; basic training at Fort Ord, California; meeting other Crow Indians while there; experiences in New Guinea fighting the Japanese; being wounded; and life after his honorable discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, June 18, 1990, Crow Agency, MT.
- BARNEY OLD COYOTE, JR. INTERVIEW, OH 1523; 2 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  Barney Old Coyote, Jr. (b. 1923) discusses his service with the U.S. Army Air Force during World War II; basic training; serving, with his brother Henry, in the 48th Bomb Group in Africa; service with Royal Navy; sinking a German submarine (U-boat); service with 47th Bomb Group on raids in occupied Europe; his Crow Indian heritage; his honorable discharge; and life after military service. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College.] Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 1991, Crow Agency, MT
- HUBERT DAWES, SR. INTERVIEW, OH 1524; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  Hubert Dawes, Sr. (b. 1928) discusses his service with U.S. Navy prior to and during the Korean War; basic training; his Crow Indian heritage service aboard the U.S.S. Current (ARS-22) and U.S.S. Hitchiti (ATF-103) off the Korean Coast; patrol and salvage missions; and his discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 28, 1991, Crow Agency, MT
- JOHN W. PEASE, SR. INTERVIEW, OH 1525; 1 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  John W. Pease, Sr. (b. 1924) discusses his service with the U.S. Army Air Force during World War II; basic and electronics training; his Crow Indian heritage; service in India with the 1309th Army Air Force Unit; flying supply missions as radio operator on various aircraft; and life after his military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn Collge.] Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 27, 1991, Crow Agency, MT.
- FRANK IRON, SR. INTERVIEW, OH 1526; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  Frank Iron, Sr. (b. 1917) discusses his service with the Oklahoma National Guard prior to World War II; posting and service with the U.S. Army 158th Infantry Division; combat experiences in the South Pacific and Philippine Islands; his Crow Indian Heritage; getting wounded; and his life after military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 1991, Crow Agency, MT.
- GILBERT W. SCOTT, JR., OH 1527; 1 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  Gilbert W. Scott, Jr. (b. 1937) discusses his experiences with the United States Marine Corps; basic training; his service with the 9th Marine Division in Japan; service aboard various ships; his Crow Indian heritage; and life after military discharge from Marine Corps. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 29, 1991, Crow Agency, MT.
- ISAAC SHANE, SR. INTERVIEW, OH 1528; 1 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  Isaac Shane, Sr. (b. 1921) discusses his service with the United States Army during World War II; his postings to various units and assignments in the Pacific; his spinal injury; his Crow Indian Heritage; and life after his military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 28, 1991, Crow Agency, MT.
- WILLIAM MEDICINE TAIL INTERVIEW, OH 1529; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  William Medicine Tail (b. 1932) discusses his service with the United States Navy during the Korean War; his Crow Indian heritage; service aboard the destroyers U.S.S. Bausell and Anderson as a gunner; and life after his military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College.] Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 29, 1991, Crow Agency, MT.
- FREDERICK TURNS BACK INTERVIEW, OH 1530; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  Frederick Turns Back discusses his service with the U.S. Army; basic training; experiences with the 40th Infantry Division and 24th Signal Company in Korea; returning to the United States on rotation; his Crow Indian Heritage; and his military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 1, 1991, Crow Agency, MT
- GEORGE PEASE INTERVIEW, OH 1531; 1 tape(s), Transcript 15 pages
  George Pease (b. 1898) discusses his military service with the United States Navy; duty aboard the U.S.S. Minneapolis and other ships; the Brooklyn Naval Yard; his Crow Indian heritage; and life after his military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, June 5, 1990, Crow Agency, MT.
- DAVID J. STEWART INTERVIEW, OH 1532; Summary 1 pages
  David J. Stewart (b. 1929) discusses his service with U.S. Army during the Korean War; training and posting with the 955th Field Artillery Battalion; his participation in major battles; his Crow Indian Heritage; and life after his military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, June 12, 1990, Crow Agency, MT.
- COLLENA L. CAPLETT INTERVIEW, OH 1533; 1 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  Collena L. Caplet (b. 1952) discusses her service in the U.S. Army; basic training; file clerk training; various duty assignments; her Crow Indian heritage; discrimination within the military; and life after her military discharge. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, June 27, 1990, Crow Agency, MT.
- CHRISTINE STOPS INTERVIEW, OH 1534; Summary 2 pages
  Christine Stops Hill (b. 1957) discusses her reasons for enlisting in the United States Air Force; basic training and special training; duty with the 321st Security Police Squadron as a Security Specialist; her military discharge; her Crow Indian heritage; later work in law enforcement; and difficulties working with men. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, March 1991, Crow Agency, MT.
- JOHN BULLTAIL INTERVIEW, OH 1535; Summary 2 pages
  John Bull Tail (b. 1922) discusses reasons he was not accepted for service during World War II; his acceptance into service after World War II; basic training; Military Police Training; service with 45th Infantry Division during Korean War; combat experiences and getting wounded on Bloody Ridge; recovery; service with 123rd Infantry Division; and his Crow Indian Heritage; his military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, October 1990, Crow Agency, MT
- ROY CALDWELL INTERVIEW, OH 1564; 2 tape(s), Transcript 47 pages
  Roy Caldwell (b. 1953) discusses his experiences as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment during Operation Desert Shield/Storm; refresher training and last-minute preparations at Fort Lewis, Washington; unit's flight to Saudi Arabia; arrival at Dhahran and temporary stay at "Cement City;" being media escort for Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS) television correspondent Bob Martin, Detroit Free Press reporter Frank Bruni, and Washington Post photographer Lucian Perkins; attitude of regular army toward civilian and military news media; various unit activities; attempting to write and publish stories and associated activities as well as associated problems; living conditions; equipment acquisitions; morale of unit at particular times; Meals Ready to Eat (MREs); equipment acquisitions; opinions of 3rd ACR troops and officers; theoretical and actual functioning of military's Joint Information Bureau (JIB); air war's beginning; recollections of ground war; future concerns for military media. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 24, 1991, Helena, MT.
- ROY CALDWELL INTERVIEW, OH 1565; 1 tape(s), Transcript 13 pages
  Roy Caldwell (b. 1953) discusses the drill weekend for the 103rd Public Affairs Detachment following the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait on August 2, 1990; and views on first anniverary of the invasion. Interviewed by John Terreo, August 2, 1991, Helena, MT.
- ROY CALDWELL INTERVIEW, OH 1566; 2 tape(s), Transcript 45 pages
  Roy Caldwell (b. 1953) discusses his experiences as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103 Public Affairs Detachment attached to 3rd Armored Calvary Regiment; regular army personnel attitudes toward civilian and military media; escorting civilian media; obtaining transportation supplies; military suppression of civilian media; and restrictions imposed by Saudi Arabian government. Interviewed by John Terreo, March 18, 1992, Helena, MT.
- MICHAEL FITZPATRICK INTERVIEW, OH 1587; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  Michael Fitzpatrick (b. 1911) discusses his service with the U.S. Army during World War II; his posting to the 66th Quartermaster Regiment which remained in the United States; his Crow Indian heritage; his hip injury; and life after his military discharge. [Originals held by Little Big Horn College]. Interviewed by Carson Walks Over Ice, February 28, 1991, Crow Agency, MT.
- RON DAVIS INTERVIEW, OH 1599; 2 tape(s), No inventory
  Ron Davis (b. 1947) discusses being drafted into the Army during the Vietnam War; basic training at Fort Lewis, Washington; Advanced Infantry training in jungle warfare; in-country training; his view of soldiers on both sides of the conflict; the goals of the War; morale; politics on the homefront; lingering effects of the War; stereotypes of Vietnam Veterans; the Wall; and his work as a DAV (Disabled American Veterans) representative. Interviewed by Amy McKinney, September 29, 1994, Helena, MT
- VICTOR LEIKAM INTERVIEW, OH 1944; 1 tape(s), Transcript 34 pages
  In this interview Victor Leikam discusses entering the Air Force in 1948, training experiences, and serving during the Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 29, 2001, Billings, Mont.
- JAMES FOLLENSBEE INTERVIEW, OH 1946; 2 tape(s), Transcript 37 pages
  In this interview James Follensbee discusses entering the Merchant Marines, serving in Montana Air National Guard, WWII service, and experiences during the Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 23, 2001, Eureka, Mont.
- DONALD NADEAU INTERVIEW, OH 1947; 2 tape(s), Transcript 26 pages
  In this interview Donald Nadeau discusses entering the Marine Corps Reserve, training received, injuries received during service, and experiences serving during Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 7, 2001, Kila, Mont.
- WILLIAM STAUDINGER INTERVIEW, OH 1948; 1 tape(s), Transcript 33 pages
  In this interview William Staudinger discusses being drafted into the Army in 1951, basic training, family military service, and service with 14th Infantry during Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 30, 2001, Laurel, Mont.
- E. LEE MAGONE INTERVIEW, OH 1949; 2 tape(s), Transcript 57 pages
  In this interview E. Lee Magone discusses enlisted in the Army in 1947, other family military service, basic training, re-enlisting, and serice during Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 21, 2001, Missoula, Mont.
- JOHN RADONICH INTERVIEW, OH 1950; 2 tape(s), Transcript 39 pages
  In this interview John Radonich discuses his family's dairy farm and growing up near Anaconda, other family member's military service during WWII, enlisting in the Army in 1950, basic training, and service during Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 28, 2001, Anaconda, Mont.
- LAWRENCE RASMUSSEN INTERVIEW, OH 1951; 2 tape(s), Transcript 59 pages
  In this interview Lawrence Rasmussen discusses being called up for duty during WWII but failing the physicals due to Rhuematic Fever, being drafted into the Army in 1951, basic training, and service during Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 18, 2001, Missoula, Mont.
- PAUL COOLIDGE INTERVIEW, OH 1952; 2 tape(s), Transcript 32 pages
  In this interview Paul Coolidge discusses entering the Marine Reserves in Shelby, Montana, going on active duty, being injured, and general service experiences during Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, September 12, 2001, Sunburst, Mont.
- JAMES KELLO INTERVIEW, OH 1953; 1 tape(s), Transcript 31 pages
  In this interview James Kello discusses entering the Marine Reserves in Shelby, Montana, going on active duty, training, and service during Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 12, 2001, Butte, Mont.
- RAYMOND HOLT INTERVIEW, OH 1954; 1 tape(s), Transcript 22 pages
  In this interview Raymond Holt discusses service with 43rd Combat Engineers during WWII, trainng, service with the 300th Field Artillery during Korean War, work for the Job Corps, and job training received in post-war through GI bill. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 19, 2001, Butte, Mont.
- GERALD NELSON INTERVIEW, OH 1955; 2 tape(s), Transcript 49 pages
  In this interview Gerald Nelson discusses being drafted into military service in 1951, basic training, and experiences during the Korean War. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 21, 2001, Butte, Mont.
- ROBERT L. TODD III INTERVIEW, OH 1956; 2 tape(s), Transcript 30 pages
  Robert L. Todd III was born in Bozeman, Montana in 1933. In this interview Mr. Todd discusses being drafted into the Army in 1953, his training, issues of race in the military, entering Korea during the armistice, living conditions for Korean people, and feelings about military service. Interviewed by Suzanne Julin, August 8, 2001, Charlo, MT
- ELMORE TINTZMAN INTERVIEW, OH 1957; 2 tape(s), Transcript 44 pages